John Camden Hotten Correspondence
John Camden Hotten Correspondence
1866-1872
Hotten, John Camden, 1832-1873.
0.25 linear ft.
Letters to and from British bookseller, publisher and author John Camden Hotten. Correspondents include poet Algernon Charles Swinburne, novelist W. Moy Thomas, writer William Michael Rossetti, and publisher Edward Moxon & Co.
3546837
Biographical History
John Camden Hotten (1832-1873) was a British bookseller and publisher. Many of the books published under his imprint were written in part or in whole by himself. In 1866 he published Algernon Swinburne's Poems and Ballads after it was withdrawn from circulation by its original publisher for "indecency." He spent several years in American and was the first to introduce a number of American writers to the British public, including James Russell Lowell, Oliver Wendell Holmes and Bret Harte. He was a Fellow of the Ethnological Society and contributed articles on literary topics to the London Review and other periodicals.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Camden Hotten Correspondence consists of letters to and from British bookseller, publisher and author John Camden Hotten. Correspondents include poet Algernon Charles Swinburne and publisher Edward Moxon & Co. A number of the letters involved Hotten's decision to publish Swinburne's Poems and Ballads, which had been withdrawn from circulation by its original publisher for "indecency." There are also a few non-letter items such as a list of sales of Swinburne's book.
Arrangement of the Collection
Chronological.
Related Material
See also the
Algernon Charles Swinburne Collection
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- British; Publishing, printing and book arts; Graham, James Lorimer, 1831-1876.; Hotten, John Camden, 1832-1873.; Howell, Charles Augustus, 1840?-1890.; Swinburne, Algernon Charles, 1837-1909.; Thomas, W. Moy (William Moy), 1828-1910.; Timmins, Samuel, 1826-1902.; Edward Moxon & Co.; Authors and publishers -- Great Britain.; Authors, English -- 19th century.; Poets, English -- 19th century.; Publishers and publishing -- Great Britain.; Correspondence.; Financial records.; Publishers and publishing.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
9 letters, purchase, 1955. Additional items, unknown.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Hotten, John Camden, no recipient, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Knight, Joseph to Algernon Charles Swinburne; to Hotten, Aug 1866; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Thomas, W. Moy to Hotten, 4 Sep 1866 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Thomas, W. Moy to Hotten, 9 Sep 1866 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Thomas, W. Moy to Hotten, 26 Sep 1866 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Edward Moxon & Co. to Hotten, 23 Oct 1866 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Timmins, Samuel to Hotten, 6 Nov 1866 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Arnold, Thomas James to Hotten, 16 Nov 1866 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Grosart, -- to Hotten, 20 Nov 1866 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Graham, James Lorimer to Hotten, 15 Dec 1866 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Huntington, W. H. to Hotten, 18 Dec 1866 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Graham, James Lorimer to Hotten, 21 Dec 1866 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Hotten, John Camden, 26 Dec 1866 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Dalston & Son to Algernon Charles Swinburne, 1 Jan 1867 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Edward Moxon & Co. to Hotten, 14 Feb 1867 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Chapman, John to Hotten, 9 Apr 1867 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Adams, C. Warren to Hotten, 2 Jun 1867 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hotten, John Camden, Jan 1868; sales of Swinburne's book (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Howell, Charles Augustus to Hotten, 16 Nov 1869 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Hotten, John Camden to William Michael Rossetti, 12 Apr 1870 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Benham & Tindell to Hotten, 2 May 1870 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Hotten, John Camden to William Michael Rossetti, 2 May 1870 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Hughes & Son to Hotten, 23 Jun 1870 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Hotten, John Camden, no recipient, 22 Nov 1870 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Hotten, John Camden to W. Moy Thomas, 24 Nov 1870 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Hotten, John Camden, no recipient, 21 Dec 1872 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Hotten, John Camden, no recipient, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)